Guide to the Eli Whitney Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Land Records, 1775-1877, undated; Series II
  Series II, LAND RECORDS, includes deeds, leases, quit claims, and other documents relating to property in New Haven and Hamden. The documents are arranged in chronological order. The earliest documents date from 1755, but probably came into the possession of the Whitney family as proof that a Whitney contemporary had title to the land Whitney was about to acquire. It is difficult to match contemporary descriptions of property against today's landmarks, but it seems that most of these land records relate to the site on the New Haven-Hamden border on which Whitney constructed his factory, to the site of his home, or to other acquisitions of property in New Haven. The extent of Whitney's land holdings is outlined in his will which is in Series V. Later records are negotiated by the executors of Whitney's estate, James Goodrich and Henry W. Edwards, and still later by his son Eli Whitney. These later records include the 1854 contract by which New Haven acquired the right to develop a reservoir for its water supply.
  The material in this series is arranged in chronological order.
  - 1755-1769 (Box 5, Folder 85, Reel 4)
  - 1770-1777 (Box 5, Folder 86, Reel 4)
  - 1779-1786 (Box 5, Folder 87, Reel 4)
    See also: box 12, folder 170
  - 1787-1795 (Box 5, Folder 88, Reel 4)
  - 1796-1802 (Box 5, Folder 89, Reel 4)
  - 1803-1805 (Box 5, Folder 90, Reel 4)
  - 1806-1809 (Box 5, Folder 91, Reel 4)
  - 1810-1812 (Box 5, Folder 92, Reel 4)
  - 1813-1815 (Box 5, Folder 93, Reel 4)
  - 1816-1819 (Box 5, Folder 94, Reel 4)
  - 1820-1827 (Box 5, Folder 95, Reel 4)
  - 1828-1829 (Box 5, Folder 96, Reel 4)
  - 1830-1839 (Box 5, Folder 97, Reel 4)
  - 1840-1843 (Box 5, Folder 98, Reel 4)
  - 1844-1850 (Box 5, Folder 99, Reel 4)
  - 1852-1877, undated (Box 5, Folder 100, Reel 4)
- Cotton Gin Papers, 1794-1959, undated; Series III
  Series III, COTTON GIN PAPERS, includes material relating to the history of the cotton gin. The bulk of the materials concern either the business partnership of Phineas Miller and Eli Whitney or the patent for the cotton gin. Documents in the series include financial records, notes and memoranda, sketches and drawings, and printed matter. Also included are two volumes of letterbooks for Miller and Whitney. These include copies of business letters as well as of letters from Miller to Whitney. The first volume contains an index to the letters contained therein, but there is no similar index in the second volume.
  The material in this series is arranged by record type and is listed in alphabetical order. The series does not include correspondence relating to the cotton gin.
  - Miller and Whitney account book, 1795-1810 (Box 6, Folder 101, Reel 4)
  - Miller and Whitney letterbook, 1794 May-1798 June (Box 6, Folder 102, Reel 4)
  - Miller and Whitney letterbook, 1798 February-1803 January (Box 6, Folder 103, Reel 4)
  - "Memoranda of Ginning Concerns" and letterbook of Eli Whitney (1820-1895), 1797-1799, 1842-1843 (Box 6, Folder 104, Reel 4)
  - Miller, Phineas: estate papers, 1804, 1806, 1818 (Box 7, Folder 105, Reel 5)
  - Financial records, miscellaneous, 1806 (Box 7, Folder 106, Reel 5)
  - Newspapers and newspaper clippings, 1795, 1796, 1802, 1885, 1901, 1923, undated (Box 7, Folder 107, Reel 5)
    See also: box 12, folder 171
  - Patent: notes, remarks, 1794, 1804-1812, 1845, undated (Box 7, Folder 108, Reel 5)
  - Patents: printed matter, general, 1805, 1807 (Box 7, Folder 109, Reel 5)
  - Patents: printed matter concerning legislative actions, 1800-1808 (Box 7, Folder 110, Reel 5)
    See also: box 12, folder 172
  - Sketches, drawings, and photographs, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 111, Reel 5)
    See also: box 12, folder 173
  - Translation of a French work on machinery by A. L. Hillhouse, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 112, Reel 5)
    See also: box 15, folder 187
  - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1822, 1898, 1915, 1959, undated (Box 7, Folder 113, Reel 5)
- Firearms Papers, 1801-1915, undated; Series IV
  Series IV, FIREARMS PAPERS, includes papers of both Eli Whitney and his son Eli Whitney, which relate to the production of guns. The bulk of the father's papers is composed of financial records relating to contracts with the government and drawings for machinery and buildings on the mill site. The numerous patents in this series are for improvements in gun manufacture during the tenure of Eli Whitney (1820-1895) as head of the gun factory.
  The material in this series is arranged by record type, which is listed in alphabetical order.
  - Financial papers: general, 1801-1815, 1821, undated (Box 8, Folder 114, Reel 5)
    See also: box 15, folder 188
  - Financial papers: account book of armory and personal expenses, 1808-1816
    See: box 13, folder 174
  - Financial papers: account book of armory and personal expenses, 1811-1823
    See: box 13, folder 175
  - Financial papers: "Certificates of Inspection of 10,000 Muskets", 1801-1809 (Box 8, Folder 115, Reel 5)
  - Financial papers: receipts for 10,000 muskets, 1801-1809 (Box 8, Folder 116, Reel 5)
  - Financial papers: vouchers for muskets, 1815-1824 (Box 8, Folder 117, Reel 5)
  - Machinery: sketches, plans, drawings, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 118a, Reel 5)
    See also: box 14, folder 176-177; box 15, folder 189-200
  - Mill site: sketches, plans, drawings, 1915, undated (Box 8, Folder 118b, Reel 5)
    See also: box 14, folder 178; box 15, folder 201
  - Musket production: Eli Whitney; (1765-1825) statement, notes, etc., 1810, 1816, 1820, undated (Box 8, Folder 119, Reel 5)
  - Patents
    See: box 14, folder 179
  - Patents, 1870-1871 (Box 8, Folder 120, Reel 5)
  - Patents, 1872-1874 (Box 8, Folder 121, Reel 5)
  - Patents, 1877-1879 (Box 8, Folder 122, Reel 5)
  - Patents, 1880-1881 (Box 8, Folder 123, Reel 5)
  - Whitney Arms, Co., 1863, 1867 (Box 8, Folder 124, Reel 5)
    See also: box 15, folder 202
  - Miscellaneous notes, lists, statements, etc., 1862, 1868, 1878-1881 (Box 8, Folder 125, Reel 5)
    See also: box 14, folder 180
  - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1803, 1808, 1822, 1823, 1853, 1869, 1885, 1893, 1906, undated (Box 8, Folder 126, Reel 5)
- Personal Papers, 1771-1914, undated; Series V
  Series V, PERSONAL PAPERS, includes papers of several family members, though the largest quantity of personal papers are those of Eli Whitney (1765-1825). These personal papers include Whitney's student notebooks and other writings from his education at Yale, a copy of a journal Whitney kept while teaching school, financial and legal papers relating to his family in Westborough, Massachusetts, and other records of his personal finances. The series also includes the papers from his estate such as his will and an inventory of his property and biographical sketches composed after his death.
  Material in this series is attributed to various family members. The material is arranged by record type. Material of Eli Whitney is arranged at the beginning of the series and is followed by material of other family members. Family members are listed in alphabetical order.
  - Eli Whitney
    - Biographical sketches, 1825, 1832, 1886, 1904, 1912, 1914, undated (Box 9, Folder 127, Reel 6)
    - Account books, 1793-1794 (Box 9, Folder 128, Reel 6)
    - Financial papers: checks, 1823 (Box 9, Folder 129, Reel 6)
    - Financial and legal papers: general, 1771-1784, 1806-1814, undated (Box 9, Folder 130, Reel 6)
      See also: box 14, folder 181
    - Financial and legal papers: Jesse Potter, 1788, 1805-1813, undated (Box 9, Folder 131, Reel 6)
    - Journal (transcript), 1788-1789 (Box 9, Folder 132, Reel 6)
    - Poems, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 133, Reel 6)
    - Porter, Samuel: diary and account book describing tour to the South with Eli Whitney (photocopy), 1803-1808 (Box 9, Folder 134, Reel 6)
    - Portraits, 1792 (Box 9, Folder 135, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: "A Dialogue between a Justice and an Attorney", 1784 (Box 9, Folder 136, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: disputes, 1789-1792, undated (Box 9, Folder 137, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: disputes, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 138, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: essay re life of deceased friend, R. Grant, [1789-1792?] (Box 9, Folder 139, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: essay on suicide and other writings, 1790-1791 (Box 9, Folder 140, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: "Extracts" (short sayings), [1789-1792?] (Box 9, Folder 141, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: extracts from essays, [1789-1792?] (Box 9, Folder 142, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: greek tables, 1789 (Box 9, Folder 143, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: mathematical theorems, [1789-1792?] (Box 9, Folder 144, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: notes on astronomy, [1789-1792?] (Box 9, Folder 145, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: notebook, [1789-1792?] (Box 9, Folder 146, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: pocket account book, 1787 (Box 9, Folder 147, Reel 6)
    - Student papers: miscellaneous papers, undated (Box 9, Folder 148, Reel 6)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1795, undated (Box 9, Folder 149, Reel 6)
  - Eli Whitney estate
    - Drafts of will and related documents, 1823-1826, undated (Box 9, Folder 150, Reel 6)
    - Inventory of real and personal estate, 1825 (Box 9, Folder 151, Reel 6)
    - Record book, 1825-1830, 1839, 1843 (Box 10, Folder 152, Reel 6)
  - Other family members
    - Chaplain, C. L. And Chaplain, Francis E. Whitney and family, 1842-1844, 1872, 1877-1880 (Box 10, Folder 153, Reel 6)
    - Edwards, Alfred P.
      See also: box 14, folder 183
      - Account book, 1825 (Box 10, Folder 154, Reel 6)
      - Bill for sponges, 1830 (Box 10, Folder 155, Reel 6)
      - re Percival case-testimony, 1826-1827 (Box 10, Folder 156, Reel 6)
      - Scrapbook and Miscellaneous documents, 1831-1834, 1847-1861 (Box 10, Folder 157, Reel 7)
    - Edwards, Pierpont: will, 1817 (Box 10, Folder 158, Reel 7)
    - Whitney, Eli, (1820-1895)
      - Letterbook, 1842-1843
        See: box 6, folder 104
      - Financial and legal papers, 1844, 1857-1864, 1871, 1888, undated (Box 10, Folder 159, Reel 7)
      - Obituary notices, 1895 (Box 10, Folder 160, Reel 7)
      - Student papers, 1831-1841 (Box 10, Folder 161, Reel 7)
      - Data on lumber, 1842 (Box 11, Folder 162, Reel 7)
      - Business diary, 1852-1860 (Box 11, Folder 163, Reel 7)
    - Elizabeth Whitney (1819-1854): miscellaneous papers, 1842, undated (Box 11, Folder 164, Reel 7)
    - Henrietta F. (Edwards) Whitney: miscellaneous papers, 1861-1865, undated (Box 11, Folder 165, Reel 7)
  - Miscellaneous papers unidentified, 1869, undated (Box 11, Folder 166, Reel 7)
- Oversize
  - Correspondence, 1796-1801 (Box 12, Folder 167, Reel 7)
  - Correspondence, 1802-1819 (Box 12, Folder 168, Reel 7)
  - Correspondence, 1837, 1882 (Box 12, Folder 169, Reel 7)
  - Land records, 1784-1856, undated (Box 12, Folder 170, Reel 7)
  - Cotton gin
    - Newspapers and newspaper clippings, 1795-1796, 1802, 1885, 1901, 1923, undated (Box 12, Folder 171, Reel 7)
    - Patents: printed matter concerning legislative actions, 1801 (Box 12, Folder 172, Reel 7)
    - Sketches, drawings, and photographs, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 173, Reel 7)
      See also: box 15, folder 203
  - Firearms
    - Financial papers: account book of armory and personal expenses, 1808-1816 (Box 13, Folder 174, Reel 7)
    - Financial papers: account book of armory and personal expenses, 1811-1823 (Box 13, Folder 175, Reel 7)
    - Machinery: sketches, plans, drawings, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 176, Reel 7)
    - Machinery: sketches, plans, drawings, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 177, Reel 7)
    - Mill site: sketches, plans, drawings, 1915, undated (Box 14, Folder 178, Reel 7)
    - Patents, 1858, 1867 (Box 14, Folder 179, Reel 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes, lists, statements, etc., 1862, 1868, 1878-1881 (Box 14, Folder 180, Reel 7)
  - Personal papers
    - Eli Whitney: financial and legal papers; student papers: disputes, 1799-1803, 1805-1814, undated (Box 14, Folder 181, Reel 7)
    - Eli Whitney estate, 1825, 1841 (Box 14, Folder 182, Reel 7)
    - Edwards, Alfred P.: permits for sailing, 1833 (Box 14, Folder 183, Reel 7)
    - Other family members: miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 184, Reel 7)
- Copy Negatives
  Copy negatives have not been filmed.
  - From box 1, folder 13 (Box 15, Folder 185, Reel n/a)
  - From box 3, folder 52 (Box 15, Folder 186, Reel n/a)
  - From box 7, folder 112 (Box 15, Folder 187, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 114 (Box 15, Folder 188, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 189, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 190, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 191, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 192, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 193, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 194, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 195, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 196, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 197, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 198, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 199, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118a (Box 15, Folder 200, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 118b (Box 15, Folder 201, Reel n/a)
  - From box 8, folder 124 (Box 15, Folder 202, Reel n/a)
  - From box 12, folder 173 (Box 15, Folder 203, Reel n/a)